Guide to the Incunabula Collection at Stanford University, 1467-1500
Department of Special Collections
Incunabula Collection at Stanford University,
1467-1500
Special Collections Various
Stanford University Libraries
178 volumes
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The collection contains 178 volumes printing during the first fifty years after moveable type printing presses came into existence. These incunabula (literally "in the cradle") works demonstrate the evolution of printing conventions during the first few decades of the new technology.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Acquired as purchases and gifts from a variety of sources
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The collection contains 178 volumes printing during the first fifty years after moveable type printing presses came into existence. These incunabula (literally "in the cradle") works demonstrate the evolution of printing conventions during the first few decades of the new technology.
Container List
- Jerome, Saint, d. 419 or 20. Beati Hieronymi Epistolas ad eruditionem Christiana[m] pernecessarias re[rum] ac materiarum uarietate confusas ... [Rome: Sixtus Riessinger, not after 1467], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1467.J46 f; 2 v.; 33 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., IV, p. 27 (IB.17432a). Goff (rev.), H-163. GW 2330. Hain-Copinger 8550. ISTC (RLIN), ih00160800.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials in red or blue with decorative tracing in the other color; paragraph marks in the table to Jerome in red. Initial of table to Jerome ([****1r]) in gold, blue, red, green and white; 1st leaf of text of Jerome ([a1r]) elaborately decorated with historiated capital and historiated floral border in gold, blue red, green and white. Imperfect: v. 1 lacks last 2 blank leaves of [**]; 1st leaf of [***]; last 3 blank leaves of [M]; all of v. 2 lacking. Binding: blind-stamped leather over boards; rebacked; leather and metal clasps. Provenance: ms. marginalia.
- Auerbach, Johannes, 15th cent. De septem sacramentis. In vrbe Augustensi impressus ...: A Ginthero Zeiner de Reutlingen ..., millesimo quadringentesimo sexagesimonono [1469], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1469 .A92 f; [98] p.; 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 315 (IB.5410). Goff (rev.), A-1381. GW 2852. Hain 2124. ISTC (RLIN), ia01381000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials, initial strokes, paragraph marks, and underscoring in red. Red capital M at top of p. [3]. Binding: half leather, brown boards. Binder's title: Summa Jo. D. Maurb 1469. Scant ms. marginalia.
- Pliny, the Elder. Libros naturalis historiae nouitiu[m] Cam[a]enis Q[ui]ritiu[m] tuo[rum] opus natu[m] apud me proxima f[a]etura licentiore epistola narrare co[n]stitui tibi iocu[n]dissime imperator. Restituit Venetis: me nuper Spira Ioannes ..., 1469., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1469 .P5 f; [712] p.; 41 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 153 (IC.19506) (variant setting). Goff (rev.) P-786. Hain-Copinger-Reichling, 13087. Horblit, H.D. Grolier 100 science books, 84. ISTC, ip00786000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Rubrication: 2 large decorated initials, one with human figure and floral border, in blue, red, green, brown, mauve, white gold ink; most large spaces blank; smaller capitals added in red or blue; initial-strokes, some headings in red. Signatures (cf. BM 15th cent.) added in pencil. Imperfect: lacks final blank (p. [711]-[712]). Binding: full calf, gilt spine; red edges. Binder's title: C. Plinii Historia natur. de anno 1468. Provenance: Christophorus Pirchaimer Viennensis (inscription); facsim. of Hilprand Brandenburg of Biberach's bookplate depicting an angel holding shield with bull.
- Durand, Guillaume, ca. 1230-1296. Incipit rationale diuino[rum] officiorum. Augustensi [Augsburg]: Gintherus Zainer ..., [22 Jan. 1470], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1470 .D8 f; [434] p.; 41 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 315 (IC.5413). Goff (rev.) D-404. GW 9103. Hain 6472*. ISTC, id00404000. Pellechet, 4492. Proctor, 1523. Stillwell, D330.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: 8 large decorated capitals with floral borders, in gold, red, green, blue, brown, mauve and white ink; smaller capitals, paragraph marks and initial-strokes in red. Imperfect: lacks first 2 leaves ([**], table). Binding: tooled leather over boards, rebacked; remains of 2 fore-edge clasps, with metal fittings stamped: aue maria gracia; metal corner guards on top corners; staple chain attached to bottom edge of back board. Provenance: presentation inscription from Johannes [Frhl de Praunerk?] and his wife Magdalena to the frm. mino[rum] reg[u]laris in Bulsano; Conventu FFr. Minor. Franciscano[rum] Bulzanensiu[m] (inscription).
- Leo I, Pope, d. 461. Iohannis Andre[a]e Episcopi Aleriensis ad Summum Pontificem Paulum ii Venetum epistola.[Rome: Johannes Philippus de Lignamine, between 7 Mar. and 21 Sept. 1470], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1470 .L46 f; [320] p.; 32 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., IV, p. 29 (IB.17429). Goff (rev.), L-131. Hain-Copinger 10010. ISTC (RLIN), il00128500.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals and some headings in red. Foliation supplied in ink (with errors); ms. marginalia (some trimmed). Imperfect: Lacks first two and final two pages (all blanks), and quire n, which is supplied in ms. on [22] p., with catchwords. Binding: full calf, marbled endpapers, red edges. Binder's title: Leo Magnus Sermones et epistolae.
- Cicero, Marcus Tullius. [Ten leaves from Io. An. Episcopi Alerien[sis] in Corsica ad Paulum II Venetum Pont. Max. epistola: M. Tullii quot et est extra numerum orationum] Rome: Conradus Suueymheym, Arnoldus Pannartz[que] Magistri impresserunt talia multa simul, 1471., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1471 .C48 F; [20] p.; 35 cm.
  Consists of 3 orations: M. Tul. Ciceronis De prouinciis consularibus oratio; M. Tul. Ciceronis P[ro] Rege Deiotaro ad C. Cesarem oratio; and M. Tul. Ciceronis Pro M. Marcello ad patres conscriptos C. Cesarem oratio.
  References: BM 15th cent., IV, p. 13 (IC.17172a). GW 6761. Goff (rev.), C-541. Hain-Reichling 5121. ISTC (RLIN), ic00541000. Pellechet 3688.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials at beginning of each oration in red and blue; paragraph marks and underscoring of headings in red. Binding: white boards; 5 blank leaves bound in before and after text. Provenance: ms. marginalia.
- Incipit libell[us] Sancti Thome de Aquino De vicijs et v[ir]tutibus numero quat[er]nario p[ro]cede[n]s.[Cologne: Arnold Ther Hoernen, February 1471-1475?], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1471 .D4; [32] p.; 22 cm.
  References: Copinger 551. Goff (rev.), T-342. ISTC (RLIN), it00337800. Oates 438. Pellechet 990. Proctor 990.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial strokes and underscoring in red; initials and paragraph marks in red and blue. Binding: full calf; gilt turn-ins and gilt corner decorations on upper and lower covers; gilt edges; title in gilt on spine; marbled endpapers. On spine: Thomas de Aquino De viciis et virtutibus. Blank leaves bound in at end. Provenance: Ex Musaeo Huthii (booklabel).
- Sanchez de Arevalo, Rodrigo, 1404-1470. Ad sanctissimu[m] et B. d[omi]n[u]m d[omi]n[u]m Paulum secu[n]dum pontificem maximu[m] liber incipit dictus Spec[u]l[u]m vite humane ... / editus a Rodorico Zamorensi ...[Augsburg]: A Ginthero Zainer ex Reutlingen ... vrbe ... Augustensi ..., [11 Jan. 1471], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1471 .S26; [256] p.; 29 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 316 (IB.5419). Goff (rev.) R-215. Hain-Copinger 13940*. ISTC, ir00215000. Proctor 1525.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: first capital on p. [1] added in red and green ink; other capitals added in red. Binding: half vellum, boards covered with early printed sheets of German text, rubricated. Binder's title: Rodericus Zamor. Spec. vitae hum. Provenance: hand-painted shield, p. [1].
- Valerius Maximus. Valerij Maximi Romane urbis iurisp[er]itissimi in libru[m] facto[rum] et dictorum memorabiliu[m] ad Tiberiu[m] Cesarem prefatio incipit.[Mainz: Peter Schffer, 14 June 1471], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1471 .V35 f; [396] p. (last p. blank); 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 27 (IB.157). Goff (rev.), V-23. Hain-Copinger 15774. ISTC (RLIN), iv00023000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: capitals, initial strokes and paragraph marks added in red; folio no. and running title added in red on 1st leaf of most gatherings. Binding: quarter morocco, diced Russia boards, with marbled endpapers and red edges. Spine title: Valerii Maximi Facta et dicta. Provenance: A.J. Canham (armorial bookplate).
- Burchardus, Urspergensis, d. 1230. Hystoria Friderici Imperatoris Magni.[Augsburg: Monastery of Saints Ulrich and Afra, 1472], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA 1472 .B8 f; [92] p.; 31 cm.
  References: Indexed by: BM 15th cent., II, p. 340 (IB5756). Copinger 2589. GW 5737. Goff (rev.), B-1285. Hain 8718. ISTC (RLIN), ib01285000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Initial large capital in red and blue, with ornate borders in red. Capitals in red and blue, several with fluorishes and scrolls; initial strokes in red; paragraph marks in red and blue; coat of arms hand-colored in black, red, and yellow at bottom of p. [3]. Imperfect: lacks final [2] (blank) p. Provenance: ecclesiastical crest of Maximilian Pagl, Abbot of Lambach, on upper cover; William Salloch (bookseller's label).
- Burlaeus, Gualterus, 1275-1345? Incipit pulcher tractat[us] coll[e]c[t]us p[er] venerabilem doctore[m] Walteru[m] Burley Anglicu[m] De vita ph[ilosoph]o[rum].[Cologne]: Per me Arnoldu[m] Ter Horne[m], anno D[o]m[ini] 1472., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1472 .B85; [196] p.; 21 cm.
  References: Goff (rev.), B-1317. GW 5783. Hain-Copinger, 4122. References: ISTC (RLIN), ib01317000. Pellechet 3095.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding order: same as in Hain-Copinger 4122. Rubrication: large capitals in red and blue; other capitals and paragraph marks in red. Binding: brown boards. Provenance: ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Isidore, of Seville, Saint, d. 636. Isidori Iunioris Hispalensis Episcopi liber Etimologiarum ad Braulionem Cesaraugustanum Episcopum scriptus incipit foeliciter.[Augsburg]: Per Gintherum Zainer ex Reutlingen progenitum literis impressi ahenis., 1472, 19 die mensis Noue[m]bris., Call No. Barchas Collection KA1472 .I8; [528] p.: ill.; 28 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 317 (IB.5438). Goff (rev.) I-181. Hain 9273*. ISTC, ii00181000. Polain 2135.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (BARCH): Rubrication: capitals added in red ink; dated at end by rubricator, 1473. Binding: stamped vellum over boards; 2 fore-edge clasps. Binder's title: Isidori episcopi Hispale Ethimolog. lib. XX. Provenance: Bibliote. ssrm Alexandri A. [Th?]eod. in Ottobeurni (inscription); Cvno Schongauiani Carmel Disc. 177[?] (inscription); ms. marginalia. Imperfect: final leaf trimmed and mounted; margins trimmed, with loss of ms. notes.
- Isidore, of Seville, Saint, d. 636. Incipit liber primus Ethimologiarum Isidori Hispalensis Episcopi: de disciplina et arte.[Strasbourg: Johann Mentelin, ca. 1473], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1473 .I8 f; [284] p. (p. [1]-[2], [284] blank): ill.; 39 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent. I, p. 57 (IC.586). Goff (rev.) I-182. Hain-Copinger 9270. ISTC, ii00182000. Polain 2133. Proctor 227. Stillwell I.154.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials added in red, blue green or mauve ink; large decorated initials at book incipits; running titles and initial-strokes in red; some illustrations hand-colored; figures added in red, Greek words in brown ink in text; guide letters supplied in ms. Imperfect: lacks [al] (blank) and [d4,5] (p. [1]-[2], [67]-70]). Binding: quarter vellum, brown boards. Binder: F. Grimm (stamp). Binder's title: Isidorus Episcopus Hispalensis. Etymologiarum libri XX. Provenance: [?] Landes Bibliothek, Strassburg (ink-stamp); K.U. L.B. Strassburg (release stamp?); Ewald Flgel (ink-stamp).
- Rainerius, de Pisis, d. ca. 1348. Ad reuerendissimu[m] in Christo patrem et dominu[m] B. miserat[i]one diuina Sancte Romane Ecclesie dignissimum episcopu[m] cardinale[m] Sabinensem, Place[n]tinu[m] vulgariter nu[n]cupatum, protectorem singularissimu[m] Ordinis Predicatoru[m] Fratris Iacobi Florentini Ordinis Minoru[m] prefat[i]o in seque[n]s opus Fratris Raiinerii de Pisis Ordinis Predicatoru[m] incipit.[Nuremberg]: P[er] industriosos imp[re]ssorie artis m[a]g[ist]ros Io[ha]nem Sensenschmid de Egra et Henric[um] Kefer de Magu[n]tia Nurmberge vrbis ciues ..., anno a natiuitate D[omi]ni [1473] [6] Idus Ap[ri]lis [8 April]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1473 .R35 f; [1730] p.; 42 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 405 (IC.7073). Goff (rev.), R-5. Hain 13015. ISTC (RLIN), ir00005000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): 407 leaves. Imperfect: lacks 1st 32 leaves (tables + 2 blanks), [r8] (blank), and all after [R6]. Text consists of entries for letters A-I. Rubrication: large initials in red, blue or red and blue; small initials, headings, initial strokes, paragraph marks and underscoring in red. Binding: blind-stamped calf over boards; rebacked; remnants of clasps; tabs for each letter of the alphabet (A-I); ms. waste used in binding. Provenance: John Stirton (armorial bookplate); Monasterij B.V. in Diessen (inscription); ms. marginalia.
- Sanchez de Arevalo, Rodrigo, 1404-1470. Ad sanctissimu[m] B. Patre[m] D.D. Paulum ii. P.M. liber incipit dictus Speculum uit[a]e human[a]e ... editus a Rodorico Episcopo Zamorensi ... Impressus est ... Rom[a]e, in domo ... Ioha[n]nis Philippi de Lignami ..., anno eius secundo ultima die mensis. Iulii [31 July] 1473., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1473 .S26; [324] p. (last p. blank) 29 cm.
  Includes index.
  References: BM 15th cent., IV, p. 31 (IB.17389). Goff (rev.) R-220. Hain-Copinger 13943. ISTC, ir00220000. Klebs 857.9. Proctor 3391. Stillwell R.214.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: tooled leather over boards; rebacked. Binder's title: Rodorici Speculum vitae humanae. Ms. marginalia and underscoring. Imperfect? lacks 2 leaves (including 1st blank?) as called for by BM 15th cent.
- Albertus, Magnus, Saint, 1193?-1280. Su[m]ma prelucidissima de mirabili Eucaristie sacram[en]to.[Ulm]: Per Ioh[ann]em Zeiner in opido Vlm diligenter impressa, anno Domini M*.cccc*.lxxiiij [1474]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1474 .A37 f; [7], lix, [1], lx-Clxxv leaves; 31 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., II, p. 522 (IB.9129). Goff (rev.), A-335. Hain-Copinger 456. GW 780. ISTC (RLIN), ia00335000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: untouched. Binding: full vellum, stamped in blind, remains of metal clasp; in case with title: Summa de Eucharistie Sacramento. Binder's title: 1474 Ulm Joh. Zainer. Provenance: Ex libris cap[itularis?] domus ecclesiae [cath.?] [Augustane?] (inscription); scant ms. marginalia.
- Augustine, Saint, Bishop of Hippo. Aurelij Augustini De ciuitate Dei Confectum Venetijs: Ab ... Nicolao Ienson, Petro Momenicho principe, anno a natiuitate Domini milesimo quadringe[n]tesimo septuagesimo quinto sexto nonas Octobres [2 Oct. 1475], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1475 .A94 F; [612] p.; 30 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., V, p. 175 (IB.19686). GW 2879. Goff (rev.), A-1235. Hain-Copinger 2051. ISTC (RLIN), ia01235000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: half tawed pigskin, brown cloth; in case. Provenance: Liber Stefani [?] papa (inscription); Albert M. Bender (inscription); Caroli ac Mariae Lacaitae filiorumque Selham, Sussex (bookplate); ms. marginalia; ms. signature notations(?) on some pages, trimmed; ms. notes in German on blank leaf at end. Rubrication: illuminated initial beginning text on p. [33]; initials in red and blue; paragraph marks, initial strokes, underscoring and fists in red. Imperfect: lacks pp. [1]-[2] (blank); lacks p. [19-20] and [29-30], supplied in photocopy, loose; Binding error: duplicate p. [17-18] (8th printed leaf) bound in; extra blank leaf preceding p. [33].
- Durand, Guillaume, ca. 1230-1296. Incipit Racionale diuino[rum] officiorum.[Basel, Michael Wenssler, not after 17 Mar. 1476], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1476 .D8 f; [412] p. 40 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 725 (IC.37101). Goff (rev.), D-411. GW 9110. References: Hain 6464. ISTC, id00411000. Pellechet 4489.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: large decorated capital in green brown ink; other capitals, initial-strokes and paragraph marks added in red. Title in ms., p. [3]: Gvilhelmi seu Guillermi Durandi, Ep. Minacensis seu Mimatensis Rationale divinorum officiorum libri VIII. Imperfect: lacks 1st leaf (blank). Binding: quarter morocco, wooden boards with remains of 2 fore-edge clasps. Provenance: Monasterio nostro Benedictenpeiren (inscription).
- Hugo, Argentinensis, ca. 1210-ca. 1270. Co[m]pendiu[m] theologice ueritatis / co[m]pilatu[m] p[er] Albertum Magnu[m]. I[m]pressumq[ue] Venetijs: P[er] mag[ist]r[u]m [Xr][ist]oforu[m] Arnoldu[m] Alamanu[m], 1476 die 5 Aprilis ... [5 April 1476], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1476 .H84; [320] p. (first 2 and last p. blank); 18 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent. V, p. 205 (IA.19988). GW 604. Goff (rev.), A-232. Hain-Copinger 439. ISTC (RLIN), ia00232000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding: half vellum, boards covered with early printed German text, rubricated. Binder's title: Albertus Magnus Com. theol. verit. Venedig 1496. Provenance: ex libris bookplate; ms. marginalia on p. [234]-[235], trimmed. Rubrication: capitals, some decorated, initial strokes, and underscoring in red. Signed and dated at end VC [1482?] by rubrisher. Imperfect: lacks the initial blank leaf as called for in BM 15th cent., V, p. 205 (IA.19988).
- Jerome, Saint, d. 419 or 20. Epistola[rum] diui Hieronymi primi uoluminis recognitionem epistola. Inpressum [sic] Rome in domo nobilis uiri Petri de Maximis iuxta Campum Flore: Preside[n]te magistro Arnoldo Pannartz, anno D[omi]nici natalis M.CCCC.LXXVI. die uero xxviii. Martii ... [28 March 1476], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1476 .J47 f; [604] p.; 39 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., IV, p. 62 (IC.17929). Goff (rev.), H-167. Hain-Copinger 8555. ISTC (RLIN), ih00167000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: Initials and paragraph marks in red. Imperfect: lacks p. [1]-[2] and [21]-[22] (blanks). Binding: full leather, blind-stamped design of trees and circles within diamonds, decorative border. Provenance: Thomas Ashby (armorial bookplate); P.S. on fore-edge; ms. inscription above colophon: Mag[ist]ri Francisci Bolognini de Rauen[n]a Ordinis P[re]dicato[rum] [sum?] Rome sub Innocentio Octavo Pontifice Maxi[m?]o M.cccc.Lxxxviiij; ms. marginalia; ms. annotations on verso of register at end; foliated in ms. (with errors).
- Vincent, of Beauvais, d. 1264. Speculu[m] hystoriale Vincentij Beluacensis fratris Ordinis P[re]dicatorum incipit.[Strasbourg: Adolf Rusch, 1476-1480], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1476 .V57 f; 4 v.; 38 cm.
  References: Copinger 6245. Goff (rev.), V-282. ISTC (RLIN), iv00282000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initials and paragraph marks in red; large initials at beginning of v. 1-2 in red and blue and of v. 3-4 in red and purple. Imperfect: lacking blank A1 in v. 1. Binding: full vellum; title label on spine; red edges; binder's title: Belvacen. Spec. Hist.; each v. in case. Provenance: Oswald Weigel ... Leipzig (bookseller's stamp); Ewald Flgel library (booklabel); ms. guide letters and marginalia.
- Vincent, of Beauvais, d. 1264. Speculum morale Vincent de Beauvais.[Strassburg: Johann Mentelin, 9 Nov. 1476], Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1476 .V58 f; [954] p.; 39 cm.
  Contents: Sequitur tabula breuis alphabetica -- Primus liber Speculi moralis -- Liber secundus -- Tercius liber Speculi moralis -- De virginitate.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 58 (IC.552). Copinger 6252. Goff (rev.), V-288. ISTC (RLIN), iv00288000.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Rubrication: initial large capital in Primus liber Tercius liber in red and blue; initials in red throughout; underscoring in blue. Imperfect: lacks p. [9]-[10] and [953]-[954] (blanks). Binding error: p. [1]-[8] misbound at end of text; p. [3]-[6] loose. Binding: full vellum over boards covered with early printed leaf with Latin text, rubricated; bound in 2 v. Binder's title: Belvacen[?] Spec. Moral; each v. in case with title: Speculum morale Vincent de Beauvais, v.1, pt.1 and v.1, pt.2, respectively. Provenance: Ewald Flgel Library (label); Oswald Weigel Antiquariat Auctions-Institut Leipzig ... (ink-stamp); ms. marginalia and fists; signatures on gatherings supplied in ms. (with errors); guide letters supplied in ms.; some loss due to trimming.
- William, of Ockham, ca. 1285-ca. 1349. Dyalogus doctoris venerabilis M[a]g[ist]ri Guilhelmi Oka[m] tres tractatus co[n]tinet: quo[rum] prim[us] qui e[st] De hereticis h[abet] septe[m] libros. Impressus Parisius: [Printer of Ockam], anno D[omi]ni 1476 die 5 Iullii., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1476 .W55 f; 2 v. ([1052] p.); 30 cm.
  Contents: Dialogorum libri septem adversus haereticos -- Tractatus de dogmatibus Johannis XXII -- Compendium errorum Johannis XXII.
  References: BN v. 126, col. 363. Goff (rev.), O-8. Hain-Copinger, 11937. Mazarine. Incunables, 136.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Binding order: 13 blank leaves; index (14 printed leaves); 1 blank leaf; Dialogorum libri septem adversus haereticos (276 printed leaves); 13 blank leaves (317 leaves total). Variant?: Hain-Copinger 11937, Mazarine. Incunables, 136; transcription differs from that cited; BN states its copy is also different. Rubrication: large initials in red, blue and gold for beginning of each book and of caption to index; small initials, initial strokes and paragraph marks in red or blue, some marked in yellow as well. Imperfect: contains only Dialogorum libri septem adversus haereticos and its index. Binding: blind stamped leather over boards; five metal bosses affixed to upper and lower covers; remnants of clasps. Edge title: Okam dial[ogii?]. Provenance: ms. marginalia and underscoring.
- Bonaventure, Saint, Cardinal, ca. 1217-1274. Regime[n] co[n]scie[n]tie vel paruu[m] bonum / editus a Fratre Bonaue[n]ture Cardinalis. [Epistola Sa[n]cti Methodij ep[iscop]i Pararensis de regnis ge[n]tiu[m] ... Tractatus de preparac[i]o[n]e ad missam ... Ioha[n]nis Bonaue[n]ture].[Cologne: Ulrich Zel, before 18 Sept. 1477]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .B656; [96] p. (last 2 blank); 20 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., I, p. 193 (IA.2978). Goff (rev.), B-970. GW 4706. Indexed by: Hain-Copinger 3498. Hain-Copinger 11124. ISTC (RLIN), ib00970000. Ohly Sack. Inkunabelkatalog, 659. Polain 801.
  Stanford copy: Stanford copy 1 (RBC): Imperfect: lacks the final blank as called for in BM 15th cent., I, p. 193 (IA.2978). Binding: tooled brown morocco. Binder's title: Bonaventura regimen. Provenance: R. Hildebrand, 1851 (inscription); The Hildebrand Library (ink-stamp), with the ink-stamp of three-petaled flower within a shield; foliated in ink (with errors); paged in pencil.
- Durand, Guillaume, ca. 1230-1296. Incipit Racionale diuinorum officiorum.[Basel: Berthold Ruppel and Michael Wenssler, not after 1477]., Call No. Spec Coll Rare Books KA1477 .D8 f; [414] p. (p. [1]-[2], [414] blank); 41 cm.
  References: BM 15th cent., III, p. 716 (IC.37024). Goff (rev.), D-415. GW 9111. Hain-Copinger, 6463. ISTC, id00415000. Polain 1373. Stillwell D338. Goldschmidt, E.Ph. Gothic Renaissance bookbindings, no. 15.